Hi, this is Matt Baker. On August 28th,
2026, King Harald V of Norway passed
away and thus Norway now has a new king,
Haakon VIII. Today, I'm therefore going
to show you the entire family tree of
Norwegian monarchs, going all the way
back to Harald I
in the year 872. I'll be using our
European Royal Family Tree North/East
Chart, which, take note, has been
updated with the new king. As usual, if
you want to get a copy of the chart as a
poster, you can do so by going to our
website usefulcharts.com
or by clicking the link in the
description or pinned comment. Also
available is a European Royal Family
Tree West Chart as well as an East Asian
Royal Family Trees Chart.
Traditionally, the first king of Norway
is said to be Harald Fairhair, who lived
during the Viking Age and who supposedly
reigned from 872 to 931. However, keep
in mind that Harald Fairhair is
generally understood to be more of a
legendary figure, being a member of the
Yngling Dynasty, who show up in Beowulf
and who supposedly descend from the god
Freyr. In reality, Norway during the
10th century likely still consisted of
several petty kingdoms. However, we do
have solid evidence for the existence of
his son, Eric Bloodaxe, not in Norway,
but in England. You see, after being
declared king in 931, Eric was soon
replaced by his younger brother, Haakon.
He thus had to flee, first taking refuge
in the Orkney Islands in what is today
Scotland, but then eventually retaking
the English city of York, which had
previously been under Viking control. It
is there that this coin was found,
dating to his reign, which says Eric
Rex. But, Eric's reign didn't last long
because in 954, he was killed in battle,
bringing an end to Viking rule at York.
Mack of Norway, Haakon I, was followed
by Eric's son, Harald II,
but then he was replaced by his uncle,
Harald Bluetooth, the king of Denmark,
who is also the person that Bluetooth,
the technology, is named after. The
Bluetooth symbol being a combination of
the runic letters H and B for Harald
Bluetooth. From here, the throne of
Norway passed back to a descendant of
Harald Fairhair, Olaf I,
but then back to the Danish king, Sweyn
Forkbeard, who also conquered England,
establishing what's called the North Sea
Empire. This union of the three crowns,
England, Denmark, and Norway, reached
its peak under Cnut the Great. But, in
between Sweyn and Cnut, Norway was
actually independent again for a while
under Olaf II.
Olaf II is important because it was
during his reign that Norway became
truly united, thanks in part to
Christianity being made the state
religion. For this reason, he is
remembered today as Saint Olaf, the
patron saint of Norway. After Cnut the
Great's death, the throne of Norway
passed back to Saint Olaf's son, Magnus
I.
And for a few years, he held the throne
of Denmark as well, becoming known as
Magnus the Good. But, in 1047, the two
countries finally went in separate
directions, with the House of Estridsen
taking over in Denmark, and the House of
Hardrada taking over in Norway. That
house was founded by Harald III,
a half-brother of Saint Olaf. During the
reign of Cnut the Great, Harald had
escaped to Kievan Rus, where he served
as a military leader under Yaroslav the
Wise. He then traveled to the Byzantine
Empire, where he served in the Varangian
Guard during the reign of Michael IV.
But eventually, he made his way back to
Norway, where he became king in 1047.
During his reign, he tried to conquer
both Denmark and England, but in both
cases, he was unsuccessful. His invasion
of England, however, became extremely
consequential for the history of that
country because it occurred in 1066.
Now, if you know your British history,
you'll know that that was also the year
of the famous Battle of Hastings, which
is when William the Conqueror defeated
Harald Godwinson to become King of
England. But here's what you may not
know. Just 3 weeks before the Battle of
Hastings, Harald Godwinson had to fight
in the Battle of Stamford against Harald
III of Norway. In this first battle,
Harald Godwinson won, with Harald III
being killed in action. However, the
battle weakened his troops, which in
turn contributed to his defeat at
Hastings. But we are concerned with
Norway here, not England. So, let's
continue down the tree. Harald III's
death is usually seen as marking the end
of the Viking Age because from here on
out, the Scandinavian kings mostly
stayed within their own realms instead
of trying to invade far-off lands by
sea. One exception to this, however, was
Harald's grandson, Magnus III. He seized
control of the Orkney Islands, the
Hebrides, and the Isle of Man, and even
became King of Dublin, albeit only for 1
year because while in Ireland, he was
killed. Back in Norway, his sons clung
onto power for a while, but pretty soon
the country fell into a period of civil
war, which lasted over 100 years. It
finally came to an end during the reign
of Haakon the Fourth, a descendant of
Magnus the Third via several
illegitimate lines. He actually became
king in 1217, but it wasn't until 1240
that he managed to reunite the entire
country. Haakon the Fourth is also
notable in that it was during his reign
that Greenland and Iceland became a part
of the Norwegian realm. Haakon the
Fourth was followed by his son, Magnus
the Sixth, who modernized Norway's law
code and finally made peace with
Scotland, agreeing that the Hebrides and
Isle of Man would become Scottish in
return for Shetland and the Orkney
Islands remaining under Norway's
control. His son and successor, Eric the
Second, even ended up marrying a
Scottish princess. Now, since this ended
up having a major impact on Scottish
history, let's momentarily switch over
to the European royal family tree West
chart, so I can explain what happened.
So, here you can see Eric the Second
shown on this chart as well, as the
husband of Margaret of Scotland, who was
the daughter of Alexander the Third.
Now, as it turned out, when Alexander
the Third died, his only living
descendant was Eric and Margaret's
three-year-old daughter, who was also
named Margaret. This Margaret thus
suddenly became the queen designate of
Scotland. However, it gets even more
complicated than that, because the king
of England at the time, Edward the
First, proposed that when they came of
age, Margaret should marry his son, the
future Edward the Second. If this were
to have happened, it would have united
the crowns of England and Scotland 400
years earlier than they actually did.
But, of course, that never happened
because at age six, while on the journey
to be crowned queen of Scotland, young
Margaret died, throwing Scotland into a
major succession crisis, one that was
eventually settled when Margaret's
fourth cousin, Robert the Bruce, came to
the throne. So, let's now return back to
the North/East chart. Eric II married
again, but never did have any sons. So,
when he died, the throne passed to his
brother, Haakon V. Eric did have another
daughter, though, named Ingeborg, and
she was married off to a Swedish prince,
as was Haakon's daughter, also named
Ingeborg. This set the stage for a union
with the throne of Sweden. Because when
Haakon V died, his only legitimate
descendant ended up being this person
here, who was 3 years old at the time,
and who, in the same year, was also
elected King of Sweden. Take note that
in Norway, he's known as Magnus VII, but
in Sweden, he's Magnus IV. Now, once
Magnus became of age, he had two sons,
Eric and Haakon. So, the plan was that
Eric would receive Sweden and Haakon
Norway. In fact, Haakon was given Norway
before his father's death, becoming
Haakon VI. However, Eric died before
Magnus, and in fact, Magnus became very
unpopular, and was eventually deposed
and replaced in Sweden by his nephew,
Albert. In Norway, Haakon VI ended up
marrying Princess Margaret, the daughter
of the Danish King Valdemar IV, a
marriage that would end up becoming
extremely consequential. You see, when
Valdemar IV died, their 5-year-old son,
Olaf II, became King of Denmark, with
his mother, Margaret, serving as regent.
But then, when Haakon VI died, Olaf II
became King of Norway as well, when he
was just nine. So, suddenly, Margaret
was now the regent of two kingdoms. But
then, Olaf himself died at age 16,
resulting in Margaret becoming Queen
regnant of both Denmark and Norway. Now,
by this point, Sweden had grown tired of
Albert, who had been born and raised in
Germany, and who had brought over many
German officials to help govern Sweden.
Therefore, several Swedish nobles asked
Margaret to help depose him and become
their queen as well, which she did in
1389. Then, several years later in 1397,
the union between the three crowns of
Denmark, Norway, and Sweden was cemented
even further with the creation of the
Kalmar Union, which would go on to last
for 126 years, aside from a few brief
years when rebels put Karl Knutsson on
the throne of Sweden and for a brief
period on the throne of Norway. Now,
whereas Sweden eventually re-achieved
its independence in 1523, Norway did
not. In fact, in 1537, during the reign
of Christian III, Norway was officially
made subordinate to Denmark around the
same time that Lutheranism was made the
state religion of both countries.
Technically, Norway still remained a
distinct kingdom after this point, but
for the next several centuries, the
crown of Norway continued to always be
held by the king of Denmark. I won't go
through all of those kings because I'll
be doing that in a separate Denmark
video. But before I zoom ahead to the
modern kings of Norway, I do want to
point out the start of the House of
Oldenburg because it ended up reigning
not only in Scandinavia, but in several
other European countries as well. As you
can see, after Margaret I,
the thrones passed first to Eric of
Pomerania, and then to Christopher of
Bavaria, both of whom were descendants
of Valdemar IV. But after this, there
were no descendants left of Valdemar IV,
and therefore Christian I
from the House of Denmark was selected
as he was a descendant of Eric IV. Now,
as you can see, the new royal house
ended up producing several junior
branches, such as the House of
Holstein-Gottorp,
which ended up inheriting Sweden for a
while, but even more importantly,
Russia. While the final seven tsars
there are considered to have been
Romanovs, via the male line, they were
actually all members of the House of
Holstein-Gottorp.
Another junior branch started from this
duke here. It became known as the House
of Glücksburg, and eventually gained the
throne of Denmark when the senior line
of the House of Oldenburg died out.
However, before that happened, the
throne of Norway ended up being ceded to
Sweden in 1814. So, for the next 91
years, it was the Swedish king who was
also the king of Norway. But then came
Norwegian independence, which was
achieved through peaceful means. It
started with a referendum in which
99.95%
of voters in Norway voted to dissolve
the union with Sweden. The government
then had to decide whether it wanted to
become a republic or choose a king. In
the end, the monarchist side won, and
while Sweden offered their king's
younger son, Prince Carl, as a
candidate, Norway ended up choosing the
future Danish King Frederick the VIII's
second-born son, who was also named
Carl. Carl agreed, but only if the
voters were okay with it. Therefore, a
second referendum was held in November
of 1905, which resulted in about 80%
voting in favor of Prince Carl becoming
king. Thus, Norway finally got its own
king, with Carl choosing the name Haakon
VII as his regnal name, which was a good
choice, considering that Haakon VI had
been the last adult king to reign in
Norway prior to the Kalmar Union. Haakon
VII reigned for 51 years through both
World War I, in which Norway was
technically neutral, and World War II,
when it was occupied by Nazi Germany,
forcing the king to flee to the UK. In
1957, he was succeeded by his son
Alexander, who took the name Olav V. A
few years earlier, Olav's wife, Princess
Märtha of Sweden, had died from illness,
and he never remarried. So, for all 33
years of his reign as king, he had no
queen. The couple did, however, have
three children before Märtha's untimely
death, including one son. So, when Olav
V died in 1991, he was succeeded by
Harald V. That was an important moment
for Norway because it was the first time
in 610 years that someone born in Norway
had become king. Harald V reigned for 35
years, and just last week was succeeded
by his only son, Haakon, who is now
Haakon VIII. Okay, at this point,
there's a few genealogical connections
between the Norwegian royal family and
other royal families that I'd like to
highlight. First of all, through his
grandmother Märtha, King Haakon is third
cousin to King Carl XVI
Gustaf of Sweden. And through his
grandfather, he is also third cousin to
King Frederik X of Denmark. But, there's
more. Haakon is also closely related to
King Charles III of the UK in two
different ways. Through his
great-grandmother Maud, he is related to
Queen Elizabeth. And through Haakon VII,
he is related to Prince Philip. You see,
Norway was not the only country to
choose a Danish prince to become their
king. Greece did as well, all the way
back in 1863, when they elected Haakon
VII's uncle George, who was also a
second-born prince. George I of Greece
was the paternal grandfather of Prince
Philip, which means that King Charles
and King Haakon belong to the same
male-only line. Now, before I go, I want
to switch over to this fan-made chart
about the Norwegian line of succession.
With Haakon VIII now being king, that
means that his firstborn child, Crown
Princess Ingrid Alexandra, is now the
heir apparent. Prior to 1971, only males
were allowed to become monarchs, and
prior to 1990, they were given
preference over females. However,
nowadays, the firstborn always takes
precedence, whether male or female.
Second in line is King Haakon's only
other child, Prince Sverre Magnus. Then
comes his sister, Princess Märtha
Louise, followed by her three daughters,
none of whom hold any royal titles. This
is because, unlike in the UK, Norway
likes to keep its royal family quite
small. Only the grandchildren of a
monarch in the direct line get titles,
and only a reigning monarch's children,
siblings, and siblings' children are in
the line of succession. This means that
once Ingrid becomes queen, her aunt and
cousins will be removed. Now, even
though Norway's royal family is
extremely small, it has been plagued by
multiple scandals in recent years.
Perhaps most controversial is the new
queen consort, Mette-Marit, who was
friends with Jeffrey Epstein and lied
about her frequent communication with
him. She also has a child from a
previous relationship named Marius Borg
Høiby, who was recently convicted for
rape and domestic abuse. Another
controversial figure is the king's
sister, Märtha Louise, who has long
claimed to be able to communicate with
angels. After divorcing her first
husband, who later committed suicide,
she started a relationship with an
American named Durek Verrett, whom she
married in 2024.
Verrett, a self-described shaman, claims
to be part alien and sells expensive
amulets that supposedly have healing
powers. Despite all of this, recent
polls have indicated that about 60% of
Norwegians still support having a
monarchy. So, will the new king be able
to increase that support? Or will he end
up being Norway's final king? Let me
know in the comments what you think. And
don't forget, if you want to get a copy
of the chart as a poster, just head over
to usefulcharts.com
or click the link in the description or
pinned comment. Thanks for watching.